DOMINIC JOHN BENNETT

Details: dominic.john.bennett@gmail.com // + 46 76 88 38 66 4 // Irish/British

Web: dominicjbennett.com // GitHub // Google Scholar // LinkedIn

Address: Nils Dahlbecks gata 5, lgh. 1401, Göteborg, 412 49 Sweden

Adept software developer/engineer, researcher and data analyst with demonstrated history in industry and academia.

7+ years of experience in software development and engineering, statistics, data analysis, (bio-)informatics as well as technical writing and public speaking; able to work independently as well as in a team; worked as professional scrum master for global software company; proven track-record in academia with multiple published scientific articles and open-source software packages; developer of own reproducible, analytical workflows; trained in the life sciences with first-hand experience with large "omic" datasets.

Experience

2020 - Present	Cloud native software engineer Scrum Master A series of work packages in networking and security for the 5G packet cloud core. Experience includes updating network interfaces to IPv6 and; developing a new microservice to enable the use of Trusted Execution Environments across a network cluster. Ericsson, Gothenburg, Sweden.
2019 - Present	Software developer, consultant <u>Layer10</u> , Gothenburg, Sweden
2017 - 2019	Postdoctoral researcher Open-source developer Developing a modular pipeline for automated phylogeny generation in R, University of Gothenburg & Gothenburg Global Biodiversity Centre, Sweden.
2018 - Present	Open-source code reviewer R package reviewer for <u>ROpenSci</u>
2015 - 2017	Online resources coordinator Quantitative Ecology Special Interest Group, British Ecological Society.
2012	Text-mining research intern for the pharmaceutical industry Nucleotide sequence discovery in scientific and legal texts. Linguamatics, Cambridge, U.K.
2010 - 2011	Researcher in population genetics Population genetics of fungus, Microbotryum. Université Paris-Sud, Paris, France.
2009	Conservation volunteer Field experience in the rainforest with Operation Wallacea. Buton Island, Sulawesi, Indonesia.

Education

2013 - 2017 **PhD** in Evolutionary Biology and Palaeobiology

Title: "An appraisal of the Living Fossil Concept", <u>link</u>. *Imperial College London & Zoological Society of London, U.K.*

2012 - 2013 MRes in Genomics and Biodiversity Informatics, Distinction

Title: "Testing for Non-random Phylogenetic Responses to Urbanisation Using Mass

Phylogeny Estimation". Imperial College London, U.K.

2008 - 2012 **BSc** in Biology with French for Science, First Class Honours

Final year thesis title: "Evolution of the Yeast Metabolome". *Imperial College London, U.K. & Université Paris-Sud, France*

Skills

Computer

Languages R, python, golang, C++, C, ttcn

Tools/Frameworks git, Docker, kubernetes, helm, apache spark

Engineering Design architecture, pipeline development, unit and functional testing

CI/CD Jenkins, Travis-CI, AppVeyor

Other LINUX, UNIX, HPC facility, Google Cloud

<u>Human</u>

Management Agile development, scrum

Academic articles 7 first-authorships, 9 co-authorships

Communication Technical writing, proofreading, teaching, presenting and public speaking

Languages French (C2), Swedish (B1), Spanish (A2) and Japanese (A2)

Open-Source Software

outsider	Install and run programs, outside of R, inside of R	CRAN, ROpenSci	R
restez	Create and query a local copy of GenBank in R	CRAN, ROpenSci	R
phylotaR	An automated pipeline for retrieving orthologous DNA sequences from GenBank	CRAN, ROpenSci	R
treeman	Intuitive manipulation of phylogenetic trees in R	CRAN, GitHub	R, C
TNR	Resolution of taxonomic names in python	<u>PyPi</u> , <u>GitHub</u>	python
pG-lt	An automated pipeline for converting taxonomic names into phylogenetic trees	<u>PyPi, GitHub</u>	python

Selected Publications						
outsider: Install and run programs, outside of R, inside of R		Bennett, D.J., Hettling, H., Silvestro, D. et al.	<u>JOSS</u>			
How the Past Impacts the Future: Modelling the Performance of Evolutionarily Distinct Mammals through Time.	2019	Bennett, D.J., Sutton, M.D. & Turvey, S.T.	Phil. Trans. B.			
Quantifying the living fossil concept	2018	Bennett, D.J., Sutton, M.D. & Turvey, S.T.	Palaeontologia Electronica			
phylotaR: An automated pipeline for retrieving orthologous DNA sequences from GenBank in R	2018	Bennett, D.J., Hettling, H., Silvestro, D. et al.	<u>Life</u>			
restez: Create and Query a Local Copy of GenBank in R.	2018	Bennett, D.J., Hettling, H., Silvestro, D. et al.	JOSS			
Evolutionarily distinct "living fossils" require both lower speciation and lower extinction rates	2017	Bennett, D.J., Sutton, M.D. & Turvey, S.T.	<u>Paleobiology</u>			
treeman: an R package for efficient and intuitive manipulation of phylogenetic trees		Bennett, D.J., Sutton, M.D. & Turvey, S.T.	BMC research notes			
Public presentations						

2019

Royal Society, link.

References

Mark D. Sutton Samuel T. Turvey

The evolutionary potential of 'living fossils'

Senior Lecturer in Palaeontology, Professor of Zoology, Imperial College London Institute of Zoology, London

 $\underline{m.sutton@imperial.ac.uk} \\ \underline{samuel.turvey@ioz.ac.uk}$